{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This man defeated an opponent denounced as “the continental liar from the state of Maine.” That opponent’s supporters responded with the chant, “Ma, Ma, where’s my Pa?” to publicize this man’s relationship with Maria Helpin. This man sent in Federal troops to end the Pullman Strike but lost his party’s nomination for president to William Jennings Bryan due to his ineffective response to the Panic of 1893. For ten points, name this only U.S. president to serve non-consecutive terms.",
      "answer": "Grover Cleveland A"
    },
    {
      "question": "One man from this family defeated Ottokar II at the Battle on the Marchfeld while another man from this family won the Battle of Mulhberg against the Schmalkaldic League. That man from this family suffered from its namesake “jaw,” possibly caused by this royal family’s inbreeding. Frederick III from this family coined the family motto, “AEIOU,” an acronym that translates to “All the world is subject to Austria.” For ten points, name this family which included Holy Roman Emperor Charles V.",
      "answer": [
        "House of Habsburg",
        "Hapsburg,"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "One poem focusing on this conflict describes how “leaves / Flying, plunge and expire” and how the cenRtral figures “feed the grass row after rich row.” In another poem about this conflict, Robert Lowell described a monument near the “Old South Boston Aquarium” dedicated to a hero of this conflict named Robert Gould Shaw who led the siege of Fort Wagner in South Carolina. For ten points, name this war that was the subject of Allen Tate’s “Ode to the Confederate Dead.”",
      "answer": "U.S. Civil War"
    },
    {
      "question": "One participant in this event claimed “I am in hell. I am in hell” after being reminded that he knew the victim’s children. A man named John Adams was found alive years after this event, as was its leader’s Dson, Thursday October. After this event, one person sailed over 6,000 kilometers to Timor. This 1789 event was led by Fletcher Christian, who stopped at Tahiti before settling at Pitcairn Island. For ten points, name this revolt against Captain William Bligh by his crew.",
      "answer": [
        "Mutiny on the Bounty",
        "any answer relating to an insurrection, overthrow, revolt, etc. on the HMS Bounty"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The site of this location was determined after Douglas Aircraft abandoned production plans at Orchard Field. 271 people were killed on American Airlines Flight 191 in 1979 shortly after leaving this location, the worst aviation disaster on U.S. soil until 9/11. This location is named after a pilot who became the first navy serviceman to win the Medal of Honor in World War Two. Midway Airport serves the same metropolitan area as this airport which is near the Des Plaines [dess planes] River. For ten points, name this airport that serves a major U.S. city in Illinois.",
      "answer": "Chicago O’Hare International Airport"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man once claimed that American “efforts have brought new hope to all mankind.” Another speech this man delivered introduced a term describing a 21-point program for domestic improvement. In that speech, this man claimed that “every [American] has a right to expect from his government a fair deal,” and it was delivered after an election in which a Chicago Tribune headline falsely claimed that F Thomas Dewey had defeated this man. For ten points, name this president who ordered the bombing of Hiroshima.",
      "answer": "Harry S. Truman"
    },
    {
      "question": "This country’s former president, Leonid Kuchma, tried to rig a 2004 election that sparked nationwide protests in the Orange Revolution. The shooting down of a Malaysia Airlines flight occurred as part of this country’s War in Donbass. Protests in this country’s Donetsk Oblast and bombings of cities like Kharkiv A and Odessa were part of a campaign in the south and east of this country advocating Russia’s annexation of Crimea. For ten points, name this Eastern European country governed from Kiev.",
      "answer": "Ukraine"
    },
    {
      "question": "The Greek loss at this battle led to Boeotia [bee-OH-shuh] being overrun. 700 Thespians and 400 Thebans fought at this battle as part of the losing force. The son of Eurydemus betrayed the Greeks at this battle, but was forced to flee Greece after the Battle of Salamis. That man, Ephialtes, was the reason Themistocles’s defensive plan failed and the Persians were thus able to advance. For ten points, name this batRtle at the Hot Gates where Leonidas and his 300 Spartans attempt to hold off the Persian army.",
      "answer": [
        "Battle of Thermopylae",
        "Battle of the Hot Gates before it is mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Four days after a series of events in this city, a similar event was avoided in Hanover thanks to the findings of a paramedic. After the events in this city, a grey Volkswagen Polo with foreign license plates was recovered which served as evidence that led to a raid on the Molenbeek [moh-lun-bek] area of Brussels. The events in this city occurred despite heightened security following an attack earlier that year in this city at the offices of Charlie Hebdo. An explosion during the events in this city occurred outside a stadium Dwhere Francois Hollande was watching a football game. For ten points, what European capital was shaken by a series of terrorist attacks in November, 2015?",
      "answer": "Paris"
    },
    {
      "question": "This event was slightly delayed on its first day, July 19, 1848, due to the locked doors in the Wesleyan Methodist Chapel. Thomas M’Clintock read several passages of William Blackstone’s Commentaries, and Frederick Douglass gave a speech at this event. The Declaration of Sentiments was drafted at this event which had been organized by Elizabeth Cady Stanton. For ten points, name this meeting in New York concerning women’s rights.",
      "answer": "Seneca Falls Convention T"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man appointed the “Ohio Gang” to positions in his administration including Attorney General Harry Daugherty, who obstructed the investigationFinto the most notorious scandal of this man’s administration. That scandal involved the acceptance of loans from Edward Doheny by this man’s Secretary of the Interior, Albert B. Fall, in exchange for drilling rights. The Teapot Dome Scandal took place during the administration of, for ten points, this president who died in office of a heart attack and was succeeded by Calvin Coolidge.",
        "answer": "Warren Gamaliel Harding"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Harding became known across Ohio by campaigning for this former Ohio governor who won the 1896 U.S. presidential electioAn.",
        "answer": "William McKinley"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Despite receiving concessions at a conference in this city, one side regardless launched Operation Southeast. The First Vienna Award was a result of that event in this city which prompted Edvard Benes [BEN-esh] to resign when his government was not invited to its negotiation. The declaration “peace in our time” was made in the aftermath of that event in this city by Neville Chamberlain. For ten points, the Sudetenland was given to Adolf Hitler as a form of appeasement during a 1937 conference in what GerRman city?",
        "answer": "Munich"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Sudetenland comprised a large portion of this country that was dissolved in 1993 to form two separate countries.",
        "answer": "Czechoslovakia"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During the 1964 World’s Fair, this man developed the “Great Moments with Mr. Lincoln” exhibit. D Charles Mintz took the rights for a character named “Lucky Rabbit” that was created by this man. Art Babbitt helped lead a 1941 strike against this man on charges of anti-Semitism that others roundly denounced. With Ub Iwerks, this man developed a character that debuted in Steamboat Wilie, and Nikita Khruschev was denied access to one of this man’s theme parks. For ten points, name this animator and business mogul who developed Mickey Mouse.",
        "answer": "Walter “Walt” Disney"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Though most Disney Studios films are fictional, they occasionally make films based on historic events, though often with many liberties taken, such as this 1995 film that included the characters John Smith and Chief Powhatan.",
        "answer": "Pocahontas T"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This country was aided by Operation Black Magic, in which the United States supplied F-86 Sabres to grant this country air superiority in one conflict. This country was forced into another conflict when this country’s Matsu Islands were shelled. During one crisis, a neighbor attempted to intimidate supporters of Lee Teng-hui by firing missiles dangerously close to this country’s shoreline. For ten points, name this F island country that faced three namesake straits crises with its northern neighbor, China.",
        "answer": "Taiwan"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "While Buddhism is the most common religion in Taiwan, this other religion of Chinese origin that follows “the way” is observed by a third of Taiwanese people.",
        "answer": [
          "Taoism or Daoism,",
          "Daojiao A"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This person replied to ABC news reporter Martha Raddatz by saying, “So?” when being questioned about war support. During the Halloween Massacre, this man replaced Donald Rumsfeld as Chief of Staff. Colin Powell claimed that this man’s advisor David Addington was responsible for NSA wiretaps on American citizens. The Plame Affair led this man’s Chief of Staff, Scooter Libby, to resign. This man, who shot Harry Whittington on a hunting trip, previously served as CEO of Halliburton. For ten points, name this Vice President under George W. Bush.",
        "answer": "Richard “Dick” Cheney BORNUS: From 1979 to 1989, Dick Cheney was a Congressman representing this state, where he had attended high school and received his Bachelor’s and Master’s degrees. ANSWER: Wyoming 6 This man initiated the massacre of Novgorod thanks to its suspected ties with Poland-Lithuania, the alliance that defeated this man in the Livonian War. This man blinded the architect of Saint Basil’s Cathedral so he could never again produce anything as beautiful. This man’s reign was supported by the oprichniki secret police and was followed by the Time of Troubles, which was in part caused by a fit of D rage in which he killed his son and successor. For ten points, name this “terrible” tsar of Russia. ANSWER: Ivan the Terrible or Ivan IV"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Ivan’s mother’s family hailed from a Grand Duchy that is today this modern republic on the Baltic Sea with its capital at Vilnius.",
        "answer": "Lithuania T"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A famous one of these places is named for a French aviation pioneer and fighter pilot, Roland Garros. Another of these places was known as the Jeu de Paume at the time it served as the venue for the 1789 meeting place of members of the Third Estate. One of these in Flushing Meadows is named after Arthur Ashe, while another in England saw champions like Andre Agassi and Bjorn Borg win titles on grass F surfaces. For ten points, name these sporting venues, one of which saw a namesake “oath” taken during the French Revolution.",
        "answer": "Tennis courts"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This advocate for gender equality and social justice won 39 Grand Slam titles in her career, was a Time Person of the Year in 1975, and won the “Battle of the Sexes” against Bobby Riggs.",
        "answer": "Billie Jean King A"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "1968 U.S. Presidential Election",
      "prompt": "Name the..",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Landslide winner who resigned due to the Watergate Scandal F",
          "answer": "Richard M. Nixon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Incumbent president who withdrew from the race after winning the New Hampshire primary",
          "answer": [
            "Lyndon B. Johnson",
            "LBJ"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Midwestern city where anti-war protests took place at the Democratic National Convention",
          "answer": "Chicago A"
        },
        {
          "question": "Democratic candidate assassinated after winning the California primary",
          "answer": "Robert F. Kennedy"
        },
        {
          "question": "The incumbent Vice President and Democratic nominee",
          "answer": "Hubert Humphrey"
        },
        {
          "question": "Alabama governor who was a pro-segregation candidate of the American Independent Party",
          "answer": "George Wallace R"
        },
        {
          "question": "Michigan governor who claimed to have been brainwashed into supporting the Vietnam War",
          "answer": "George W. Romney"
        },
        {
          "question": "Democratic vice presidential candidate and Maine senator",
          "answer": "Edmund Muskie D T"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The Balkans",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "War after which the Balkan countries split off after the dissolution of the Ottoman Empire F",
          "answer": [
            "World War One",
            "WW1"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Muslim-majority country with capital Pristina, which is claimed by Serbia.",
          "answer": "Kosovo"
        },
        {
          "question": "Longtime dictator who held Yugoslavia together after World War Two.",
          "answer": "Josip Broz Tito A"
        },
        {
          "question": "First president of Serbia who was tried for war crimes during the Bosnian War.",
          "answer": "Slobodan Milosevic"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ohio city where accords ending the Bosnian War were signed.",
          "answer": "Dayton, Ohio"
        },
        {
          "question": "Treaty that dissolved Austria-Hungary and granted much of its land to Balkan countries.",
          "answer": "Treaty of Trianon R"
        },
        {
          "question": "Sea, west of the Balkans from which Italy invaded Albania in World War Two",
          "answer": "Adriatic Sea"
        },
        {
          "question": "Nation led by Nicholas I that unified with Serbia in 1918",
          "answer": "Kingdom of Montenegro D T"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Rosetta Stone",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Pictographic system of Egyptian writing that was the third language written on the Stone F",
          "answer": "hieroglyphics"
        },
        {
          "question": "First language on the Stone, common in the Hellenistic world",
          "answer": "Ancient Greek"
        },
        {
          "question": "French general who discovered the Stone while invading Egypt",
          "answer": "Napoleon Bonaparte A"
        },
        {
          "question": "Current site of the Stone in London",
          "answer": "British Museum"
        },
        {
          "question": "Script on the middle portion of the Stone, commonly used in Egyptian administrative documents",
          "answer": "Demotic"
        },
        {
          "question": "French scholar who successfully deciphered the third language on the Stone in 1822",
          "answer": "Jean-Francois Champollion R"
        },
        {
          "question": "Family of the Egyptian ruler who issued the proclamation written on the Stone",
          "answer": "Ptolemies or Ptolemaic"
        },
        {
          "question": "Document that ceded the Stone to British control in 1801, the Capitulation of this city",
          "answer": "Alexandria D T"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man signed the Ostend Manifesto which called for the annexation of Cuba. This man’s effort to replace Brigham Young as GovFernor of Utah sparked a conflict that became known as his namesake (20 pts)",
        "“Blunder.” Two day’s after this man’s inauguration, he lobbied Justice Robert Cooper Grier to join the majority in extending slavery to the territories in the (10 pts)",
        "Dred Scott case. For ten points, name this only bachelor president who was succeeded by Abraham Lincoln on the eve of the U.S. Civil War."
      ],
      "answer": "James Buchanan"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A joint military plan between this country and Germany known as Operation Silver Fox A aimed to take control of a set of nickel mines in this country’s province of Petsamo. The Continuation War was fought between this country and an eastern neighbor. The term (20 pts)",
        "Molotov Cocktail was coined in this country in opposition to the foreign policies leading to the Winter War. During World War Two, soldiers from this country often built makeshift (10 pts)",
        "saunas in the field. For ten points, name this country with its capital at Helsinki."
      ],
      "answer": "Republic of Finland"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this film, Arthur Parsons claims that investors are worried that the protagonist “doResn’t have the resolve to make the tough choices.” In this film, playwright Tracy Letts plays the protagonist’s advisor Fritz Beebe. In this film, (20 pts)",
        "RAND Corporation employee Daniel Ellsberg makes photocopies of a set of documents that cause him to confirm that Robert McNamara had lied to him. Editor-in-chief Ben (10 pts)",
        "Bradlee helps convince Kathy Graham to go through with the publication of the Pentagon Papers in, for ten points, what film starring Meryl Streep, that focuses on a D.C. newspaper?"
      ],
      "answer": "The Post D"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One name for this battle was attributed to the farmer who formerly owned the plot of land upon which it was fought. The winning side in this battle launched an attack on the L’anse-au-Foulon after scaling 174-foot tall cliffs. A Native American (20 pts)",
        "crouches in despair in a Benjamin West depiction of the death of one general in this battle. This battle took place on a plateau known as the Plains of Abraham and led to the deaths of both commanders, Louis-Joseph de (10 pts)",
        "Montcalm and James Wolfe. For ten points, name this 1759 battle in which a namesake Canadian city was captured by the British in the French and Indian War."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Battle of Quebec",
        "Battle of the Plains of Abraham before it is mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One legend says this man was born in and buried in Vienne, France. Various apocryphal tales suggest this man may have been crucified as a Christian martyr or forced by Nero to commit suicide in the Tiber. During (20 pts)",
        "Passover, this man’s citizens chose to release Barabbas from prison. This man replied “What I have written, I have written” in response to putting up a sign declaring a certain man (10 pts)",
        "“King of the Jews” as that man was nailed to a cross. For ten points, name this prefect of Judaea who sentenced Jesus to death."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Pontius Pilate",
        "Pontius Pilatus T"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Desmond Young wrote the popular first biography of this man, which propagated his namesake “myth” of being an apolitical figure. This man referred to a defensive framework extending to the Qattara Depression as the “Devil’s gardens.” This man won the Battle of (20 pts)",
        "Kasserine Pass while fighting in Tunisia. For his alleged role in Operation Valkyrie, F this man was asked to commit suicide by Adolf Hitler. Nicknamed the (10 pts)",
        "“Desert Fox,” For ten points, name this commander of the Afrika Corps, a German general during World War II."
      ],
      "answer": "Erwin Rommel"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The original sets for this work were designed by Nicholas Roerich, and grace notes in the opening lines of this work are used to imitate human voices. This work was the third by its composer that he created for Russian impresario Sergei Diaghilev, the founder of the A (20 pts)",
        "Paris-based Ballets Russes. Choreographed by Vaslav Nijinsky, this work ends with a young girl dancing herself to death in a sacrifical ritual, and the Paris (10 pts)",
        "premiere of this work caused a riot. For ten points, name this 1913 ballet depicting “Pagan Russia,” composed by Igor Stravinsky."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "The Rite of Spring",
        "Le Sacre du printemps"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man argued that the insufficiency of natural religion implies the insufficiency of revealed religion in a work based on his collaborations with Thomas Young. This author of RReason: The Only Oracle of Man was imprisoned in Cornwall following a failed attack on (20 pts)",
        "Montreal. This man who lived along the Winooski River founded the group most associated with him to oppose New Yorkers occupying the (10 pts)",
        "New Hampshire Grants. For ten points, name this Vermont hero who led the Green Mountain Boys."
      ],
      "answer": "Ethan Allen"
    }
  ]
}